This is Software Engineering Radio, the
podcast for professional developers on
the web at se-radio.net.
SE Radio is brought to you by the IEEE
Computer Society and by IEEE Software
Magazine online at
computer.org/software.
Hi, my name is Nikhil and I'm a host
with Software Engineering Radio. Today,
it is my pleasure to introduce Deepti
Sigireddi from Vitess. Deepti is a
technical lead for the Vitess project.
She's a software engineer at PlanetScale
where she leads the Vitess open source
engineering team. Prior to Vitess,
Deepti had spent most of her career
working on large-scale supply chain
planning problems in the retail space.
She has spoken more than once about open
source and cloud-native conferences
about Vitess
and is one of the experts in the
technology.
Welcome to the show, Deepti.
Hi, Nikhil. It's great to be here.
So, just let's get into it. So, what is
Vitess?
Vitess is a project that was started at
YouTube in 2010 to solve YouTube's
scaling problem. At that time, YouTube
had grown so much that they were having
outages almost every day because the
infrastructure could not keep up with
the kind of traffic they were getting
and this was primarily database
infrastructure. Because YouTube had
started with MySQL and they were running
many, many MySQL instances and they all
had to be managed. Some of the
engineers, including Sukumaran who's
currently the CTO at PlanetScale, got
together and decided that they needed to
solve this problem once and for all.
That whatever temporary band-aids they
were putting in place were not cutting
it and they were not going to work at
all looking at YouTube's trajectory. So,
they got together and they started
trying to solve this whole issue of you
have maybe hundreds of my sequels where
you have manually sharded, where you
have manually allocated different my
sequels to different applications and
each application is talking to its own
database or set of databases and all
these things have to work together in a
coherent manner. So, that's a little bit
about the very beginnings of Vitess. It
evolved over time to become a much more
general purpose scaling solution for my
sequel databases or you can even think
of it as a distributed database where
you don't really care about what's
behind the scenes. It just presents as a
single relational distributed database.
The team at YouTube donated Vitess to
the Cloud Native Computing Foundation in
early 2018.
Even though Vitess was open source from
the very beginning the right was owned
by Google until it was donated to CNCF
and now it is owned by CNCF. The license
is Apache 2. There is a maintainer team
consisting of 20 odd people working at
various companies. We have hundreds of
contributors and the way we count
contributions include non-code
contributions. So, documentation, filing
issues, verifying issues, all those
things count. Over the last 2 years
we've had 400 plus contributors from
more than 60 companies.
And there is a vibrant community around
it. We have a slack workspace with
around 2,700 members.
That's a great introduction. What
specifically
is the problem that Vitess is targeting
to solve? You said that it is involved
in scaling database or it can be even
considered a distributed database. Could
you go a little bit into what is that
that problem that of scale that you're
trying to solve?
These days when people build
applications, every application is
essentially a web application. You have
to have a web interface and users
interact with applications through the
web. So, every application has to be
scalable, reliable, you have to maintain
availability. Users don't like it if
they are not able to connect to your
application.
What happens then is that
these requirements, the scalability and
availability requirements, that are
necessary at the application level start
percolating down the stack and you start
requiring the same sort of scalability
and availability from your database
layer, or I want to say data layer,
because
the data layer
is not necessarily always relational,
not always what we have conventionally
thought of as databases.
So, at the data layer, if you want to be
able to scale, meaning today I have a
thousand users, tomorrow I may have
5,000, or next month I may have 10,000,
can I easily grow? What happens if
something goes wrong? If there is a
failure, what is the recovery mechanism?
How automated is that? How much manual
intervention is required? How much time
do people have to spend on call trying
to figure out what went wrong? So, these
are all problems at the business level
or application level that start
percolating down
into the data level, and that is the
problem that Vitess is solving.
And so, you mentioned that, you know, it
it's it's solving this data problem. We
also have, obviously, the
standard RDBMS databases like MySQL,
MariaDB, Postgres, etc.
How is it that those databases are not
able to do what Vitess can do. What is
the problem with the just using a
regular MySQL DB for all of this?
The thing with MySQL is that
the traditional way of scaling it has
been to put it on bigger and bigger and
bigger machines. Over time, MySQL has
built replication, so you can get high
availability. MySQL has a feature called
group replication where you establish a
quorum before you write anything so that
you get the durability. Even if one
server goes down, there is another
server that can accept writes. So, your
MySQL or the entire database doesn't go
down.
So, things have been evolving in that
direction in the RDBMS space as well. It
is not that whatever Vitess is doing,
other people are not trying to solve.
If we want to talk about Postgres,
there was a company called Citus Data
and there is a product called Citus,
which was acquired by Microsoft, which
does something very similar to what we
are doing for MySQL in Vitess.
The problem with the vertical scaling,
putting things on larger and larger
machines, is that either you outgrow the
most expensive hardware you can buy or
you can't afford to buy the expensive
hardware you need for your scale.
The other problem is that as you grow
the database larger and larger,
recovery times become longer if
something fails. So, if you take a
MySQL, you can grow it larger, you can
replicate it, you can do the group
replication so that you have a fallback,
you can do all of those things. But, you
don't natively have something like
sharding where you can keep your
individual MySQL databases small and
there is a layer that figures out how to
combine data from different individual
MySQL databases and present a unified
view.
And that's what Vitess is doing. So, we
keep the databases small, you can run it
on commodity hardware that keeps the
cost down, and there is no practical
limit to how big you can get because you
can just keep adding servers.
Is there anything special that needs to
be done if I were to adopt Vitess as my
data layer? So, in the application,
should I need is there anything special
that I need to do?
So, it really depends on what the
application is doing and how it's
written.
So, it may be as simple as just changing
the connection string to point to your
new Vitess-backed database.
Or maybe there are some features that
you get with MySQL 8.0, which are new in
MySQL 8.0, that the application is using
which are not yet supported by Vitess.
So, it really depends on the queries
that the application is producing. So,
typically the migration path we
recommend is that you take your existing
database, assuming it's MySQL. If it's
not, then the migration looks different.
And you put a Vitess in front of it
without sharding,
and you start running your queries
through Vitess.
And then you can flip a switch that
says, "I'm sharded." But
not really, you are still just uh
one shard. So, really unsharded, but a
mode where you can get errors that would
happen if you were really sharded as
warnings. And then you can work through
them.
And once you work through them, then you
are ready to
fully adopt Vitess and go into sharding
and things like that.
So, one quick question out here. We
mentioned that Vitess is a layer on top
of MySQL, and you pointed out that there
are some features of MySQL that are not
yet supported. Can you kind of quickly
elaborate as to what is the supported
surface for the Vitess project right
now?
So,
almost everything that MySQL 5.7
supports is supported. I think the only
exception to that is that if you want to
use views, then it doesn't quite work
in a sharded environment. It still works
in an unsharded environment. And the
same thing for stored procedures or
functions. They have to be managed at
the MySQL level, not at the Vitess
level. So, except for those couple of
caveats, everything should work
with 5.7.
In 8.0, a lot of new syntax was
introduced. And some of them we have
added support for. So, we are in the
process of
doing that compatibility with MySQL 8.0.
So, there are people running in
production today with MySQL 8.0 with
Vitess, no problems, because they don't
use common table expressions or window
functions or some of the JSON functions
we don't yet support. We support a
subset of the JSON functions, not all of
them. And like I said, the compatibility
work is ongoing. And when I check on it
every once in a while, I can see how
that list is getting smaller and
smaller. We have tracking issues on
GitHub, and I can see the checkboxes of
what we now support.
So, is MySQL MySQL itself has couple of
flavors, right? So, there is the
official MySQL, and then there are
couple of other projects like MariaDB
and Percona and all of that. What about
those? Are Are they also supported, or
is that kind of different?
Until fairly recently, we supported
Enterprise MySQL, Community MySQL,
MariaDB, Percona. We still fully support
Enterprise MySQL, Community, and
Percona. Percona is pretty much
indistinguishable from my sequel except
they have patches in
they have bug fixes that they keep
carrying on their newer releases.
MariaDB is different. So, we had support
for MariaDB. There were people who were
running on MariaDB or trying to run on
MariaDB, but they have run into problems
because
MariaDB has diverged quite a bit from my
sequel. We actually have an open RFC
proposing that we will officially drop
support for MariaDB sometime next year
when 10.2 goes to end of life. 10.4 is
where the compatibility starts breaking.
Right. Okay. Cool. So, coming back to
how Vitess scales the data layer, can
you talk a little bit about the
cluster topology? So, how how does
uh Vitess Vitess kind of shard and kind
of create I mean, how does it do the
horizontal replication that that it
does?
Okay. So, there are two facets to the
cluster management. One is availability.
So, we always run or the recommended way
of running Vitess is you always run it
in a primary replica configuration.
There may be people who are running it
with just primaries, which means that if
the primary goes down, you have
downtime. It's an outage. But, the
recommended configuration is primary
with replicas. And the replicas are
keeping up with the primary so that if
the primary has to be taken down for
maintenance, you can do a planned
failover, no disruption to client
traffic. If there is an unplanned I
don't want to call it downtime,
unplanned failure. Let's say the primary
goes down, there is some disk failure or
my sequel ran out of memory or something
like that, right? Then there are
primitives in Vitess that let
a human take an action, basically a push
of a button to fail over to one of the
replicas, and then the system will start
functioning again.
One of the projects that is in progress
is to totally automate this. Even in an
emergency situation, Vitess should be
able to detect and do an auto failover
without human intervention.
And we are very close to making that GA
in the next release, 14.0, which will be
out in a few months, uh around that
should be GA. So, there is that
availability aspect to it. Then there is
the scalability aspect, which is where
sharding comes in. So, you have your
whole database when you shard, what
you're doing is you're saying, "I will
store a subset of the data
on each server, and together
a group of servers will have all of the
data. And what that means is that your
data can keep growing, and you can keep
breaking it up
across more servers. So, maybe you have
250 GB of data, it's fine, MySQL will
run fine, no problems, one shard with a
primary and a couple of replicas is
good. But let's say you grow to 500 gig,
1 TB, 2 TB. The recommended size is 250
gigs. So, you may say, "Okay, when I get
to 300 or 350, I'm going to go to two
shards. When I get to 600 or 700, I'll
go to four shards."
And Vitess can transparently make this
happen behind the scenes while
applications are still connecting to the
database.
So, when you say transparently
do it behind the scenes, is there some
kind of hardware or infrastructure
setup that needs to be done, or is it
like switching a just
changing a val- value in some kind of
config?
Or do you think that that I mean is that
is there kind of like a
uh you know, a config file that you need
to modify and say hey, this is the new
server that is going to be the new
replica, etc.
That's a great question. So, when I say
transparently, it's transparent to the
client applications that are connecting
to the database. So, whoever is running
the Vitess system still needs to
provision hardware. When you increase
the number of shards, there is a
hardware cost to it, whether that is
bare metal or VMs or a cloud
environment. Somebody has to provision
the additional hardware. And like you
said, there is a configuration file
where you specify whether things are
sharded or not. And for each table, you
will also specify the sharding scheme.
So, there is a config file that has to
change when you first go from unsharded
to sharded.
But, if you're already sharded and you
want to split one of your shards, then
there are commands that Vitess provides
which will do that for you. So, you can
say, I want to reshard and my source is
X and my destinations are going to be
this set, Y, let's say, right?
Or ABC. Then, Vitess will figure out
what the
boundaries are for the sharding keys and
it will copy all of the data from the
original shard to the new shards
and it will keep them up to date until
an operator is ready to say, "Okay, I'm
ready to cut over. Let's stop using the
old shard. Let's start using the new
shards." So, there is a lot of human
intervention or orchestration in this
process,
but that is somewhat by design because
resharding is somewhat of a scary thing
to do and you want to be able to have
these checkpoints where you can sort of
pause and run some checksums or we
provide a diff tool that can do a diff
between the source and destination,
which takes a long time to run because
you are comparing gigabytes of data
or hundreds of gigabytes of data. And
then when you're comfortable, you can
actually say, "Okay, I'm ready to
switch."
And when you switch, you can say, "Can
you, by the way, keep the source in sync
with the new shards so that if something
goes wrong or we made a mistake, we can
quickly fall back."
Right.
And then redo it.
Awesome. So, I mean, so it basically
sounds like, okay,
other than the little the planning that
you need to do to make sure that you
have the necessary hardware and planning
to understand, okay, these are the
tables I'm going to re-shard and and and
making those decisions.
Most of the other work basically Vitess
handles in the sense of making sure the
database is the so the data is moved
over and that it is synced up and it it
keeps the maintenance you can switch
over smoothly.
Right. Okay, awesome. Let's kind of like
go into maybe some of the basic concepts
of what a Vitess database is like,
right? So, I happened to be looking
through the Vitess documentation, which
is quite extensive, and there were
certain terms that I thought might be
good that we could discuss in the
podcast. So, let's start with this term
of what a cell, right? So, what is a
cell and how does that work?
A cell is a failure domain. So, it is
the unit where if something fails, maybe
everything fails. That's a possibility,
right? So, it could be a cloud region, a
cloud availability zone, or if you're
running on bare metal, it may be a rack
or a server. So, people can define what
the cell looks like, and the The of
having multiple cells is to is to be
able to reason about failures. So,
people can say, "Okay, I've deployed
Vitess in this availability zone from
Amazon or this zone from Google. What
happens if the whole thing goes down?"
It's rare, but it happens, right?
Then you can say, "Oh, then maybe I
should create another cell in a
different availability zone and
replicate into that so that even if
one AZ goes down, the other one is up."
Defining cells in your Vitess topology
allows you to plan for failures at the
infrastructure level.
Okay.
Just a quick question over there. So,
can you actually define cells that are
geographically separated? So, can I have
like one cell in America and another
cell in Europe, say?
Yes, you can do that. And in fact,
YouTube ran with replicas all over the
world. Their primaries were located in
North America, but they had replicas
everywhere. And those were different
cells.
Obviously, that's kind of like a
base-level infrastructure concept. On
top of that, then there is this concept
of a key space. So, can we What is a key
space and how does that work?
So, a key space is basically a
distributed database or distributed
schema. You can
think of it as a schema in MySQL terms.
So, in MySQL on a single database
server, you can have multiple schemas.
In Vitess, in a single Vitess cluster,
you can have multiple key spaces.
And a key space is a logical database
that can physically be backed by
multiple servers, multiple replicas,
shards. All of that is part of one key
space.
Okay. The way to kind of think of it is
like I can call it my
So, if I have like a I don't know
e-commerce site, this would be the name
of the logical set of tables that we
call in the database in my sequel,
right? Okay, cool. And so, obviously
that is the logical thing. It is
distributed over many physical
databases. The next concept over there
would be the shard, right? So, because
that would be one level down from the
database. So, can you describe what is a
shard from the perspective of it does?
A shard is a subset of the key space.
So, let's say your key space spans 10
tables and let's say one of them has 100
rows, right? 100 just because that's a
simple number to work with. Now, let's
say you want to have four shards. Then
those 100 rows will be distributed
across those four shards in some
fashion. They may not be 25 25 each.
Maybe they're 22 28 27 somewhere there.
But each row in a key space lives in one
shard and only one shard. And every row
in a key space lives in some shard. So,
in mathematical terms, if you think of
your data as a set,
then the shards comprise a partition of
that set.
So, to quickly kind of like double click
a little bit over there. So, you said
that a shard or a data row can live
exactly in one shard,
right? So, don't you think from that
that that's kind of a problem? So, what
happens if that shard dies? Do you It It
means that that data is no longer
available, right?
So, this is why you do the primary
replica configuration. So, in each
shard, you have a primary and you have
multiple replicas.
So, total shard failure is very rare
because it's going to be very rare that
all of your nodes in that shard go down
at the same time. And you could
distribute each shard across multiple
cells.
So, every shard can live in every cell,
and that way you get fault tolerance to
even total zonal failure.
The cell, we've got the key space that's
a logical grouping of the database, and
then there's a shard,
which is logically one partition, but
physically you have multiple copies of
it.
The next concept, I guess, would be how
you manage all of this, right? So, uh I
saw there's this idea of a tablet in
Vitess. So, what is a tablet, and what
does that do?
A tablet is
basically a management component over
MySQL. All the data is stored in MySQL
instances,
but we need something that can say,
"Well, this is the primary for this
shard."
And we need to let everybody else who's
involved in this distributed system know
that this is the primary.
Or we may need to start and stop
replication. So, let's say we are doing
a failover from the current primary to a
new one.
There are some MySQL level actions you
need to take with the appropriate
commands so that you can elect the new
primary, and you can make the old
primary now change itself into a replica
and start replicating from the new
primary. So, these are the sorts of
management things that the tablet does.
The tablet can watch the replication and
make sure that if
it's managing a replica, and for any
reason replication breaks, try to
restart it.
So, is a tablet basically running as a
separate server component, or is it
client that can connect to the cluster,
and is it like a control plane concept
of Kubernetes?
It is a separate process. Typically, it
runs on the same server machine, okay,
physical or virtual, as MySQL, and it
connects through the Unix socket. So,
connecting through the Unix socket means
that a lot of security things you don't
have to worry about.
Right. So, for every my sequel pod or
node that you have in your cluster,
there is a tablet that is running along
with it.
Yeah, that's basically like a thin layer
sitting on top of the my sequel.
Right.
Awesome. Okay. Cool. That makes sense.
So, the next obviously way is to think
about, okay, now you have a cluster of
machines and this is the Vitess cluster,
how do you actually connect to it? So,
there is the a proxy there is concept of
a VTGate proxy. So, could you talk a
little bit about that?
You are exactly right. You have all of
these many my sequel instances with VT
tablets managing them. How does the
client know who to talk to, right?
So, VTGate is the one that lets Vitess
pretend to be a single database. So, we
give the illusion that it's a single
database. You have a single connection
string that you can use to connect to
this VTGate or basically
server address and a port. People
typically run it on the standard my
sequel port 3306.
VTGate can speak the my sequel protocol.
So, any my sequel client can connect to
it including JDBC my sequel clients, Go
lang my sequel clients, Python my sequel
clients.
Even the Ruby built-in my sequel client
works with VTGate. It also It can also
support a GRPC. So, clients which
implement the GRPC protocol can connect
to VTGates using that protocol.
And the thing it does is that it routes
queries to the right place. So, let's
say we get a simple query select XYZ
from some table where X equals 10.
VTGate is the one that figures out where
should I go look for this data.
And if it is unsharded, it's simple. It
just sends it to the unsharded primary.
If it is sharded, it has to figure out
the routing. And for more complex
queries, it may have to send the query
to multiple shards, either all shards or
a subset of shards.
And it may have to consolidate the
results. So, maybe there are rows in
like three different shards where x
equals 10 is a match, then it has to
combine all of them and return the full
result set to the client.
Then this particular proxy, depending on
how complex the query is, how how
complex the cluster is, can be a
significant
machine or a node, right? It probably
takes up a lot of your resources as
well.
Correct. Correct.
have replication for this? So, what
happens if your proxy goes down?
You can have any number of VTGates. So,
what people usually do is they benchmark
and they size the VTGates to their
traffic. And they may People will always
run at least two, maybe three.
But some installs of Vitess run hundreds
or thousands of VTGates.
What kind of scenarios of needs that
kind of
There are users of Vitess where they are
processing millions of queries a second
and they are trying to keep each VTGate
at maybe
50 to 100,000 queries a second.
So, just like you can scale your back
end as your data grows, you can scale
the VTGates as your query volume grows.
Right. And basically, does that mean
that at some point, I mean, especially
for that particular scenario that you
mentioned,
you probably want to have a proxy in
front of the proxy to kind of figure out
which
Yes. Yes.
which proxy to go to, right?
Correct. So, what people do is they run
load balancers. So, a load balancer will
receive the query and it will basically
do some sort of round robin across the
VT gates.
Or maybe you've deployed your
application through a CDN in various
parts of the world and behind the CDN
you have a smaller set of VT gates,
which will receive the traffic.
Okay. Cool. Yeah, yeah. That makes a lot
of sense. So, there's another particular
term that I came across your
documentation called the topology
service, which I was quite curious
about. What is this topology service and
what does it do?
What the topology service does is it
stores the cluster state so that
different components can discover each
other. So, really the component that
really needs to discover everybody else
is VT gate because it needs to know
which tablets it can route to. So, when
a VT gate comes up, it will be able to
read what key spaces exist, what shards
exist, which tablets belong to each
shard.
The other piece of information we store
there right now, which in theory you
don't have to, is which is the primary
tablet for a shard. So, let's say you
add a new replica. You decide that, oh,
I have a primary and two replicas, but I
want to add two more replicas for
whatever reason.
Those replicas have to discover which is
the primary tablet that they should
start replicating from and they do that
by consulting the topology service. So,
metadata about the cluster is what is
stored in the topology service.
Is it possible to then query that
metadata to understand is there kind of
like a monitoring tool that you can
build or is is it available for Vitess?
The metadata stores we support are etcd,
Zookeeper, and some people use console.
All of them are well-known tools which
which come with their own APIs. So, it
is possible to query them directly.
But, we also have a client.
So, Vitess comes with a client that you
can use to say,
"Get me a list of the key spaces. Get me
a list of the shards in this key space.
Get me a list of all the tablets that
you know about." And what the client
will do is it will talk to a server, a
control plane server, which will query
the topology server, and it knows how to
convert that the binary data it receives
from the topology server into structured
data that the clients can consume.
Thanks. That kind of gives an overview
of how the Vitess uh is set up, is laid
out, right? It's kind of like an
overview of the architecture.
Uh but, obviously, what the main main
thing that Vitess does is use sharding
to kind of scale horizontally. So, uh
perhaps, at least for uh users, it might
be useful to go a little bit into what
is database sharding
and how that works, and and how does it
help scale a database?
We talked a little bit about this
already, so we'll go a little deeper
now. To recap, sharding is the process
of splitting up your data into subsets
and storing or hosting those subsets on
different servers, physical or virtual.
And the reason we do this is because
smaller databases are faster. You can
improve your latency, but you can also
improve your throughput. You can serve
more queries in the same time because
you have more computer resources, and
there's less contention within the
database when you split them up this
way.
And we can support more connections. At
the MySQL level, usually people
configure MySQL with some max
connections number based on their
workload. Let's say that's 10,000, or
I've seen 15,000, but not more than
that.
But with Vitess gates and the way we do
things, we can actually support hundreds
of thousands of connections or millions
of concurrent connections. As to how the
sharding actually happens, we talked
about how there will there is some
configuration that you have to set up
and then the process will start. The way
it works is that Vitess will first
create the necessary metadata. So, let's
say we are splitting one shard into two,
it'll create those two shards
in the metadata. And then the operator,
the person who's running this has to
provision the tablets for that shard and
start them up and say that, "Okay, these
are now the new tablets."
Then what Vitess can do is it will say,
"Okay, I need to now start copying the
data and because we write only to
primary in each of the destination
shards, I'm going to start writing into
the primaries." So, in each of the
destination shards, I'm going to start
what is called a V replication stream.
And that V replication stream will copy
data from the source to the destination.
And the source is given to it as a key
space shard specification. So, it
consults the topology server to say what
tablets are available that I can stream
from. And it will choose one of the
available tablets. And it'll start a
copy process.
Okay, just a fundamental thing. How
granular can you make a shard? Right? Is
it kind of like at the level of a table?
Can you go smaller than a table? Can you
have like a set of tables to become a
shard? How does that kind of work?
Sometimes people will split tables out
into another key space. This is what we
call vertical sharding or move tables.
So, let's say you have 10 tables, two of
them are very big and eight of them are
small. You don't have to horizontally
shard all of them. Maybe you just move
those two large tables into their own
key space first. And then you can shard
that key space while keeping the smaller
tables unsharded. So, there is vertical
sharding and there's horizontal
sharding.
So, a shard can contain a subset of
tables
or it can contain a subset of the data
in a subset of all of your tables.
Right. So, it is Is it possible for
Vitess to have, say, like like you
mentioned, I have this huge single table
which is like my primary table which is
my OLTP table that has a lot of data in
it, but there's a lot of kind of like
reference tables and master data tables.
It's a few rows, but you keep them for
the configuration data set, right? So,
is it possible to have like those tables
not in any shards, but just this big one
in its own key space and and then just
shard it?
Yes, that's definitely possible.
So, if that is the case, then how does
that kind of
work when it's like you're running a
query which has joins in it, for
example, right? So, you would have to go
to one shard for some of the data and
another shard for the other data.
Don't you think that's kind of like
doesn't it have a performance
implication?
That's an excellent question. So, Vitess
supports cross key space joins. So,
Okay.
it can happen.
But, there is a feature in Vitess called
reference tables. So, what you can do is
you can say that these are my reference
tables which are in this unsharded key
space, but replicate them into the
sharded key space. So, then every shard
in the sharded key space will have a
local copy
of the reference tables which is kept up
to date with the with the single source
of truth, and joins become local.
Ah, okay. And since those tables aren't
very big, it's acceptable overhead.
Exactly.
Right. Is there any particular type of
joins which are
let's say less optimized or I mean is
there any kind of optimization you can
do around your SQL querying
to make your performance on Vitess
better?
There is a tool that comes with Vitess
called VTExplain, to which you can
provide what your planned sharding
scheme is and number of shards, and it
can simulate what your join will end up
actually looking like. So, the client is
issuing one query, but behind the scenes
maybe we have to do a bunch of selects
from a bunch of shards, and then use
those results and issue another bunch of
selects from the same or different
shards, and then combine all of them,
right? So, it'll actually show you that
plan. What does that plan look like? And
people use this tool, VTExplain, to look
at what the what their query plan will
look like in Vitess terms, how it's
being routed, how it's being
combined, maybe there's an aggregation.
And that can be used to then,
if desired, rewrite the query so that
they result in more efficient plans.
We do also do some optimizations during
the query planning. So, we build up an
in-memory representation of the query
that lets us
basically do relational algebra on them.
So, maybe you built up a tree
representation of the query, and it's
possible to take a filter which is at a
higher level and push it down to the
lower level. What that then means is
that you're combining smaller sets of
data together
after filtering versus combining two
large subsets of data and then filtering
on that. So, we can do optimizations of
that sort during the query planning.
Okay. And that that would be
So, is that something that happens like
transparently and the client doesn't
care or is that something that can be
helped or is there kind of like a hint
that we can give?
So, it happens transparently. It happens
in Vitess during query planning.
There are some query comments
hints that we support, but very few and
I don't know if there are any that
actually affect the planning.
Okay. So, the data is basically now
written in multiple shards and you have
obviously in the configuration file you
probably specify
okay, I want so many copies of the data
so the shards basically have so many
copies created, replicas created.
How do you actually optimize that,
right? So, because you might be getting
like certain queries that happen a lot
and that kind of affects only certain
parts of the
database, right? So, you might have your
large OLTP database, it's a primary
database, it's always getting queried,
but there may be some other user-related
user service data data that's not
queried quite so often and you want to
kind of maybe it's kind of like even
like time series data so it is time
sensitive, right? They may be querying a
lot on the recent few days versus a year
ago. Is there any optimizations that
Vitess does
that kind of help improve the
performance from that perspective?
A lot of this is sort of Vitess cluster
architecture that people design
themselves. So, if you have tables which
are less frequently used and they are
not typically queried in joints with the
more frequently used tables, then you
may just put them in a key space that is
not resource so heavily. You run it on
smaller machines.
There are a couple of things Vitess does
do for you in order to reduce the load
on the system.
One of them is what we call query
consolidation. Some people call it query
deduplication. So, the VT tablet layer,
which is in front of MySQL, receives the
query that it is supposed to execute
from VTGate and passes it on to the
MySQL and then gets the results and
sends them back.
So, it knows what are all the in-flight
queries when I receive a new query.
And if it so happens that
there is a query that's already
in-flight and I've received 10 identical
queries. Same query, same bind
variables, same where clause, same
values, everything the same. Then what
VTTablet will do is it will not issue
those
additional 10 queries to the MySQL.
It'll say, "I'll queue them and as soon
as the first one returns, I can return
all of these because they have the same
result set." So, if you have uh like a
a hot row in terms of reads,
a row that is being queried a lot, then
this actually says, "We will not do the
wasteful work of querying the same data
over and over and over again."
Okay, so it has its own kind of cache of
the
Right. Right. Of the results.
Yeah. But it's a very short-lived cache
because as soon as you start caching,
you start getting into staleness
problems.
Yeah.
So, it's extremely short-lived.
There is a leader which is currently
executing. There are followers that are
waiting. As soon as the leader returns,
all of the followers that are waiting
return. Then the next one you get will
become a leader. So, at that point,
effectively you've cleared your cache
and you have no staleness.
Right. Okay, cool.
There's one other feature, which is
again, maybe there is a row that is
being written to very frequently and
that can cause contention at the
database level.
If many transactions are trying to
operate on the same range of data, which
we compute in some way, then we'll
actually say
let's not create contention at the
database level between all of these
transactions. Let us
at the VT tablet level serialize them so
that only one of them is hitting the
database at any given time.
Okay.
So, is that something similar to like
when you say serialize, right? You're
talking about serializing at the tablet
level, right? So, at at a particular
shard level.
You still have the replication happening
independently and copies of this data is
being kept over in in multiple
tables, correct?
Correct.
Okay.
So, is there any kind of restriction or
constraint around
Okay, can I set up Vitess in such a way
that I say, "Hey, okay, this data that
I'm writing is important. I need to make
sure that
it is there and it is or available. Can
I control it so that it works or it
rather the transaction commits only
if it has been written to multiple key
spaces or multiple shards or something
like that?
Okay. So, we should talk about
durability
and then we should talk about
cross-shard transactions. So, the
default replication mode for MySQL is
asynchronous. So, you write to a primary
as soon as that gets written
to disk or however MySQL decides that
the transaction is complete, it returns
to the client. And any replicas that are
receiving binary logs from the primary,
there is no acknowledgement. There's no
guarantee that anybody has received
them. They are just following along at
their own pace.
But MySQL does have a semi-synchronous
replication mode. This was originally
developed at Google and then it became a
part of standard MySQL.
What happens in semi-synchronous
replication is that the primary is not
allowed to respond to a client with a
success for a transaction until one of
the replicas acknowledges that it has
received that transaction. It doesn't
have to write it to its tables. It just
has to have received it because what
receiving means is that the replica has
written it to its disk in a file called
the relay log. So, the primary has been
logs, sends them to the replica. The
replicas relay log gets written when it
receives the binary logs. And then once
it's applied those relay logs to its
copy of the database, then its binary
log gets written. So, there is
semi-synchronous replication which if
you enable it and set the time out to
basically infinite, you don't let it
time out
so that you're guaranteed that if the
primary returns success for a
transaction, then it has persisted on
two disks, not just one disk. So, that
gives you durability. You don't control
this at the client level. It is a server
setting. There are other distributed
databases that let you choose some of
these settings at the client level, but
in MySQL, it's a server setting.
Right.
So, that is the durability of a
transaction that a client has been told
has been accepted.
So, this way even if the primary goes
down, you're guaranteed that you can
find that transaction somewhere.
Now that we have an idea of how MySQL
ensures that you have at least two
copies, I guess the question would be do
you need to have semi-synchronous
replication in order to have a
distributed transaction or can you have
this and can you even set it to be a
little bit more strict than just the
two-way application that
semi-synchronous allows.
It is possible to set the number of
acknowledgements you should receive
before the transaction is completed. So,
MySQL lets you set that. Most people set
it to one because two failures in two
different disks are unlikely.
But, you can set it to two
acknowledgements. Then, it will be
written to three places before it
succeeds. But, you sacrifice latency for
durability, for higher durability at
that point.
Okay, cool. So,
one thought that occurred at that time
was
does this work across availability
regions? Right, so suppose you've
configured your Vitess shard to be
across multiple regions,
can I then say, "Hey, okay, I want to do
a distributed transaction where I want
it to be in two availability regions?"
That's another great question. So,
people do do this. So, they will have a
cell in one avail- one AZ, they'll have
another cell in another AZ, and they set
up replication between them and
configure Vitess in such a way that
unless you receive an acknowledgement
from a different availability zone, the
transaction doesn't complete.
It introduces a little bit of latency.
So, if you're in the same region, AWS,
but different availability zones, people
have measured this.
The latency is about additional latency
is about 150 milliseconds. So, you're
adding that much time to each of your
transactions, but that's a a tolerable
additional latency.
Right. Moving on to another question,
right? Which is
regarding the queries itself.
You mentioned that Vitess has this
internal query planner that figures out
the best way to execute the query across
across shards, right? How does that
actually improve? Do you actually have
like a Is that kind of like something
that's part of MySQL's
road map, or is that something that
Vitess kind of creates and improves on
its own? How does that actually get
better?
Okay. So, the way it gets better is that
we have a team working on it. 5 years
ago, the query planning was rewritten,
and we called it V3. And last year, we
rewrote it again and called it Gen 4,
and we are planning a Gen 5. So, this
team that specializes in query serving
and query planning, they are going out
and reading the research on how you can
build better query plans and applying it
to our specific use case of you have a
query, it'll be cross-sharded, what's
the best way to execute it.
Okay.
So, that's how we get improvements.
And that's probably why you're not so
you don't support that many hints from
the client anyway because
it kind of restricts the way then you
can you can kind of improve your query.
Correct. Correct. It's unlikely that
Sometimes this can happen, but in
general, it's unlikely that the human
has enough data to
improve
up with the best best hint, right? Which
works under different circumstances. So,
maybe it works for today's workload, but
doesn't work for tomorrow's workload.
Cool.
So, moving on to another question, we
talked about how Vitess uses the VTGate
server and the VTGate concept to
basically
have so many database connections,
right? So, a MySQL connection is not
kind of like a In a MySQL server,
connections basically are pretty heavy
weight. You have you can't really go
beyond 10 15,000 connections. It starts
becoming a bottleneck for the database.
How does having millions of connections
on a VTGate, doesn't that need to get
translated into
MySQL connections at the end of the day,
right? So, how how do you kind of
optimize that so that it doesn't affect
the MySQL load?
The way you do it is through connection
pooling. And connection pooling has
become a pretty standard thing for
people to do now. So, for Postgres,
there's a tool called PG bouncer. There
are tools like HAProxy. So, there are
or ProxySQL. So, there are many tools
that have implemented this connection
pooling concept. Even frameworks. So,
Ruby on Rails, you say, "I want a
connection pool." And you just use those
pool connections. So, the way this
improves what you can do at the MySQL
level, the way you can support hundreds
of thousands or millions of connections
at a VTGate level with, say, 10,000
connections at each backend MySQL level
is that
typically, not all of those connections
are active at any given point in time.
If you look at an end user, what they
are doing, let's say I go to a web
application or even a desktop
application. I bring up Slack. I'm
reading through messages.
I don't need to be executing a query
against the database every millisecond,
right? Maybe the way the Slack app
works, every second it fetches new
messages and shows me. So, most of the
time it doesn't actually need a database
connection or need to use the database
connection.
So, instead of a dedicated connection to
the backend MySQL for each end user, you
say, "We will give you a super
lightweight connection at the VTGate
level, which is just a session, a few
bytes of data. And when you really need
to access the backend MySQL, then we
will take a connection from a pool.
And we will use that connection, fetch
the data, and return the connection to
the pool. Connection pools can also get
exhausted, but you've now increased the
size of or the number of connections you
can support by 10x or 100x.
Right. To kind of discuss that a little
bit more. So, one of the things I have
noticed at least when I'm working with
systems is that, you know, there is this
microservices architecture model, right?
And one of the usual things that happens
with microservices architecture is that
every microservice has its own database.
But, they put all of the databases on
the same physical machine, right? So,
it's kind of you end up kind of like,
why are we doing this again? But, one of
the challenges or one of the bottlenecks
that end up happening is that
each microservice kind of then, like you
said, using the Ruby framework or the
Python framework, they'll create a
connection pool of 10 connections, say.
And then, very rapidly you will run out
of connections because you have every
microservice is holding on to 10
different connections, say.
Obviously, it sounds to me that Vitess
basically is a is a is a nice way to
kind of handle that particular
architectures this particular problem.
But, I have one thought on that was
that, okay, microservices by definition
are independent, right? So, if you have
multiple
microservices for whatever reason,
they're kind of having, say,
write transactions or they're doing
work, right? You might actually have the
situation where you have different
connection pools
that are
all holding on to heavy connections. So,
it's not that that idea of having the
lightweight thread
does not necessarily always work because
you might have
maybe multiple processes or multiple
clients from the Vitess perspective will
be multiple clients all trying to do
heavy writing work, maybe not
necessarily to the same table, but to
the same database.
Right, right. Like you said, if there
are thousands of services and each of
them has a connection pool of 10 or 20,
then maybe you will run out of what you
can support at the back end. And the way
people have solved this problem,
so what we are calling microservices,
people have typically called them
applications. So we have Vitess installs
where they do have hundreds of
applications because they've structured
their system in such a way that it's not
monolithic.
So what people tend to start doing then
is to start splitting the data out into
key spaces. Because if you have a
separate key space, then you basically
have a separate Vitess cluster with your
own compute. It's not going to be
interfered with by some other key space.
So maybe you group your microservices
and say, "Okay, this group of
microservices gets this key space and
this group of microservices, which is
not in no way connected to this other
group at all, can have its own key space
and they don't need to talk to each
other at all." So that's what people
have done.
Right. So you can use the key space
concept to kind of break that out.
Right.
Into its own set. Okay, that's pretty
cool.
Right. So that you no longer have a
monolithic database which is a
bottleneck at the back end, you have
multiple smaller databases.
Right. Okay. So moving to another
question over here is So obviously one
of the things about RDBMSs and databases
is acid compliance, right? So how does
one actually do
or how does Vitess support acid
compliance? Is it completely acid
compliant or is that like a NoSQL thing
where it is
not fully acid compliant?
If you're in unsharded mode, Vitess is
fully acid compliant. It's no different
from MySQL. But when you go sharded,
then you are a distributed system, a
distributed database, and some of those
guarantees start to break down. And we
can take like each of them one at a
time. So, the first one is atomicity. In
Vitess, there are three transaction
modes. You can say single, in which case
multi-shard transactions are forbidden
and you'll get an error.
And there are people who run it that
way. The default is multi, which is like
a best effort. So, what you do when the
transaction mode is multi is first you
figure out which all shards will be
involved in this transaction, and you
begin the transaction. So, you can do it
in three phases: begin, write, and
commit.
The The begin and write can be combined
into one phase. So, you basically open a
transaction on each shard that is going
to be involved, and you write the data,
but you don't commit it. And you do them
in parallel. So, you may write in
parallel to like three or four shards.
So, you've written the data. The
transaction is still open. It's not been
committed.
So, then what you do is that you start
committing in sequence. So, one at a
time. And if any commit fails,
you basically say, "Okay, this is a
failure." And you stop at that point.
So, what that means is that a failed
trans- multi-transaction in Vitess is
not atomic.
Some data has been written, some data
has not been written. It's possible for
the application to repair it
by reissuing the same write,
as long as it's item potent. For
example, if you're doing an If you're
doing an update, no problem, right?
Update set to the same value is fine.
Let's say you're doing an insert. Maybe
the insert does insert ignore or insert
on duplicate key update or something
like that. Then you can reissue the
transaction. Maybe this time it
succeeds.
But by default, in case of shard level,
then you can reissue the transaction.
Maybe this time it succeeds.
But, by default, in case of a shard
level commit failure, you don't get
atomicity for these types of
transactions. That is atomicity, the
default behavior. We do have a two-phase
commit protocol. So, if you set the
transaction mode to two-phase commit,
then you get atomic transactions in the
sense that it's all or nothing. So,
there is a coordinator process, we write
the metadata, we go through the state
transitions for the distributed
transaction. There is prepare and commit
and then complete or failed. And at the
end of it, either all of it has been
written or it has failed.
And if something has failed, then we try
to resolve it.
So, if something has not succeeded after
a certain time period since it started,
then one of the VT tablets, which
realizes that, "Oh, this transaction is
still in a failed state." will try to
resolve it.
So, we have two-PC transactions,
but they come with a cost because they
will be significantly slower than the
best effort multi-transaction mode. So,
that's atomicity. So,
do you want to ask any follow-up
questions before we go on to
consistency?
No, no. I think I think we're good. So,
we talked about two-phase commit, we
talked about multi, which is the same
one. So, yeah, please go ahead.
Okay. So, the next one is consistency.
For a traditional RDBMS,
all that is meant by consistency is that
any database level rules have to be
respected when you write a transaction
to the database. So, this is uniqueness
constraints, maybe you've set some
checks on particular values, maybe you
want to provide a default value, there's
a not null check, or there is an auto
increment, then the system must make
sure that the next value you write
doesn't collide with any of the previous
values. So, these types of database
level constraints. That is what
consistency means for like a single
database.
In a distributed database, you sort of
have to re-implement some of these
things. So, in Vitess, we may have four
shards, and if somebody wants a column
value to be unique, then we, at the
Vitess level, have to ensure that that
column value is unique across all of
those shards.
And we can do that if that column is the
sharding scheme, because
for a given value of the sharding
column,
we can make sure that it is unique. The
other one is auto increment. So, we
can't just have people doing auto
increment at the MySQL level, because
then in different shards, they will end
up with the same values, because you'll
start at 1 1 2 3 4 in each shard. So,
Vitess provides something called a
sequence that you can use to do auto
increment in such a way that it is
consistent across all of the shards.
Okay.
When you said that the sharding scheme,
you can be consistent in a column, a
unique column, if the column is the
sharding scheme. Does that mean that
each shard would have a separate
partition or a separate set of
values for that column?
Yeah, pretty much. So, when you get the
value, you have to figure out which
shard to put it into,
and you compute some sort of a function
on that value, and that tells you which
shard it goes into.
How does it actually work for if you
have
like so, okay, so if I've got a hundred
rows and I've said four shards, that
means that the first one zero to
twenty-five would be in one shard,
twenty-five to fifty would be in
another, fifty to 75 would be in
another. Then the last shard would
basically be anything above 75. Is that
Well,
it depends on how you define the
sharding scheme. So, Vitess has many
different sharding schemes. The simplest
one which gives you good distribution is
hash. So, if you have a numeric column
and you hash it, then you'll get a good
distribution. You won't get this sort of
overloading of one shard. Right?
But there is a sharding scheme called
numeric. You can do that, too. Maybe
your application is producing random
numbers and numeric is a good way to
shard them. There are like seven or
eight built-in sharding schemes. For
example, if you have a string column,
then you can do Unicode MD5 type of
algorithm on it.
You can do XX hash. So, there are a
a handful, I would say about eight or 10
built-in functions that you can use to
do sharding.
Or you can do custom sharding. You can
say everything in this range goes to
this shard.
Okay.
Or something like that. Any type of
custom sharding, any function you can
build on top of those values
you can do with Vitess. It's extensible.
Right. Okay. Awesome.
I think let's talk about the rest of the
acid and then we can wrap up. We talked
about atomicity, consistency, then
isolation. So, what is isolation?
There are different of isolation that
databases define. Read uncommitted, read
committed, repeatable read,
serializable. There are all these
things. But in general, what isolation
means is that if a transaction is in
progress and I am reading the data,
either I should see all effects of the
transaction or none of the effects of
the transaction. That's what typically
people want.
So, that's not read uncommitted, that's
read committed. What happens in Vitess
if you are writing transactions in the
multi mode is that you don't get the
read committed isolation.
What you get is sort of like read
uncommitted because you can see
intermediate states of the distributed
transaction. This people have started
calling fractured reads. So, maybe in
one shard you see what what the
transaction wrote and from another shard
you see the state before the
transaction. And there are now papers on
how you can provide better guarantees
around reads
when you have a distributed transaction.
So, some of that work we will probably
do in the future. We are researching
what will be a good model to provide
what sort of guarantees do we want to
provide optionally because all of these
things will slow things down. That's
isolation and we'll quickly talk about
durability.
So, at a database level durability
basically means data's not going to get
lost. If I told you that I accepted your
data then I cannot lose it.
In the past that meant writing to stable
storage disk. Now we think that's not
sufficient because disks can also be
lost. If you have 10,000 nodes maybe one
of them goes out once a year, right?
So, that's where the semi-synchronous
replication comes in and we achieve
durability through replication.
Great. Okay. So, just moving on a little
bit, I think it's safe to kind of go
through the I mean skip considerations
about the replication and stuff like
that. I think we discussed that already,
but there is one thing that I wanted to
kind of talk about which is change data
capture. So, how does Vitess handle
change data capture?
We have a feature in Vitess called V
replication and that is the basis for
our re-sharding as well.
And what that allows us to do is because
it's very flexible in terms of what it
can read, if you're doing re-sharding,
you want to copy all the data. So, the
query you give to VReplication is select
star, right? But, you can select a
subset of the columns.
Or, you can perform some simple
aggregations on columns and extract that
as a stream from Vitess, and then you
can send it to any of your applications
that want to process those changes,
those events.
Is this stream that you're calling the
call this Is that a continuous
It doesn't have to be.
It doesn't have to be. So, you can say,
"Start receiving the stream. You can
stop You can stop and record what was
the position that you got last."
And then you can come back later and
say, "Now, can you give me everything
that changed after this position?"
Huh, right. Okay.
But, how do you actually get that
position in a cluster because you might
be actually having
data in different data in different
shards, right?
We have something called VGTID, Vitess
global transaction ID,
which contains that information. So,
it'll say, "For this key space shard,
this is the MySQL GTID. For this other
key space shard, this is the MySQL
GTID." So, this is like a distributed
global transaction ID.
Nice. Okay, cool. So, then I can use
that
to say that this is the position that I
I I was at. I want to move forward from
there.
Right, right. And if you send it back to
Vitess, Vitess knows how to interpret
that and then start sending you the
changes from those positions.
Right. So, how does Vitess manage
backups, logging, and and you know, the
standard things that most SQL databases
have to handle, right?
Is Is there anything specific we have to
do if it is a cluster?
Vitess has a built-in backup method
where we just copy the files.
But we also support Percona's
XtraBackup. And typically anyone who's
running a Vitess cluster will take
regular backups
because if a replica goes down and you
lose the disk, the way to bring it back
is to restore from a backup, point to
the current primary, and then start
replicating the delta
since the back backup was taken.
And binary logs become very big and
start consuming a lot of disk space, so
people purge them on a regular basis.
And this allows you to recover failed
replicas or add new replicas
without storing all the binary logs from
the beginning of time.
All right. In a reasonably large Vitess
cluster, you probably have at least 20,
30, maybe nodes, right? So, is there
Does Vitess kind of have kind of just
like your management topology, the the
client does it have a client or a tool
that we can
use to know that, okay, I've completed
the backups for X out of
Y nodes and I need to do the rest?
Okay. You can use the same Vitess client
to list all the backups for a keyspace
shard or all the backups for a keyspace.
And using that, you can figure out when
was the last time I took a backup for a
particular shard.
I don't think we do a great job of
showing progress while a backup is in
progress.
Okay.
That is That is kind of written just to
the VTTablet log.
But you still know from the from the
topology that, okay, X out of Y tablets
have been
backed up, and what was the last time
that it was backed
Correct. Correct. Yeah. Yeah. It's
possible to infer that. This is a great
point. These things can be improved.
We talked about binary logs and how they
can become really big. In some
architectures, basically, logging is
kind of trying to They try to centralize
logging. They send logs to a different
place and stuff like that, right? Is
there something like that here or is
that still managed through MySQL
standard?
Right now, it is still up to the
operator of the Vitess cluster to manage
these things,
like setting the bin log retention
period and things like that.
There are some thoughts of building a
Vitess-compatible binary log server so
that all replicas can replicate from
that, and that replicates from the
primary. That will reduce the amount of
binary logs you have to keep. There are
some thoughts around doing something
like that, but we are not actually
working on that right now.
Okay. So, we talked a lot about the type
of work and scaling that Vitess does.
I'd also kind of like to get your
viewpoint on what kind of scenarios is
Vitess not suited for, right? So, it's
kind of like a negative thing,
but you obviously everything every
architecture has its pros and cons.
There are certain things that it's not
suited for. So, what is
the For what kind of architecture, what
kind of solution I should not be looking
at Vitess? I should I should look at
something else.
So, analytics is or OLAP workloads is
one thing that, in my opinion,
relational databases, the row-based
ones, are not very well suited for.
Columnar databases are much better
suited for analytics workloads. So,
may may not be a great idea to use
Vitess if what you're trying to do is
data warehousing.
Okay.
Any final thoughts that you might want
to mention that I missed in talking
about Vitess with you or just in
generally if you want to kind of follow
up.
I think one thing that is
pretty much unique about Vitess is that
A, your sharding scheme is flexible and
different tables can have different
sharding schemes. This other distributed
databases do provide.
But you can go from unsharded to sharded
and back from sharded to unsharded. So,
you can merge shards.
And you can even do M to N. So, let's
say you have three shards and you want
to go to eight or you have eight shards
and you want to combine them into three
because you over-provisioned when you
split up your key spaces and this
particular key space is not getting that
much traffic or whatever reason, right?
The other thing you can do is you can
change your mind about your sharding
key. There is a cost which is you have
to provision additional hardware and
copy everything over into your new
sharding scheme, but you can say, well,
uh I thought that
I'm a multi-tenant system and tenant ID
would be a great thing to shard on, but
look, I have these huge tenants and I
have these tiny tenants and that's not a
good data distribution. So, I'm actually
going to change my mind and shard it by,
I don't know, user ID or message ID or
some other transaction ID, right? That
is possible. You can do that in Vitess.
In most systems, once you've made your
sharding decision, you cannot go back.
Awesome. Thank you so much Deepti for
spending above and beyond with me and
going so deep into Vitess.
I'm sure our audience would be very
interested to know how to contact you or
if where to kind of find you and follow
you.
I'm on LinkedIn. I'm on Twitter. Do join
our Vitess Slack. I'm usually in there
answering questions. Visit the Vitess
website. We have some pretty decent
examples to get people started off.
Visit the Planet Scale website
and you can reach me on any of these
social media spaces.
Awesome. Awesome. And I'll I'll put your
Twitter and your LinkedIn links in the
show notes
so that we can reach out to you. Thank
you so much, Deepi. Have a nice day.
Thank you, Nikhil. This was really
enjoyable and I appreciate the
opportunity.
Thanks for listening to SE Radio, an
educational program brought to you by
IEEE Software Magazine. For more about
the podcast, including other episodes,
visit our website at se-radio.net.
To provide feedback, you can comment on
each episode on the website or reach us
on LinkedIn, Facebook, Twitter, or
through our Slack channel at
seradio.slack.com.
You can also email us at
team@se-radio.net.
This and all other episodes of SE Radio
is licensed under Creative Commons
License 2.5.
Thanks for listening.